Guide to the Douglas Bennet Papers, 1940 - 2004
Douglas Bennet Papers,1940 - 2004
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Bennet, Douglas Joseph.
2009-32
50
118 archival boxes.
Bennet graduated from Wesleyan University, class of 1959, and was president of that institution from 1995 to 2007. These professional papers contain materials from his undergraduate studies, including materials from Bennet's position as co-president of fraternity Alpha Chi Rho. There are also materials from his graduate studies at the University of California, Berkeley, and at Harvard University. The bulk of the materials cover his professional career, beginning as administrative assistant to Ambassador Chester Bowles in India in the mid 1960s, and continuting through his many years in Washington D.C. He was a speech writer for Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey from 1967 to 1968 and the collection contains realia from the 1968 Humphrey/Muskie presidential election. In the early 1970s, Bennet was an administrator, first for senator Thomas F. Eagleton and then for Abraham Ribicoff. As administrator for Senator Eagleton, he helped craft the Democratic Platform in the 1972 election and was active in Eagleton's political campaign. Bennet ran for the House of Representatives in 1974 and went on to be the staff director for the newly-formed Senate Budget Committee from 1974 to 1977. Bennet served twice as Assistant Secretary of State, as Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional Relations from 1977 to 1979, and as Assistant Secretary of State for International Affairs from 1993 to 1995. He also served as administrator for the Agency for International Development (AID), 1979 to 1981. The AID series contains many photographs. This collection also contains material on Bennet's two years as president of the Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies and some material from his ten years as president of National Public Radio. The personal series includes a family scrapbook containing a 19th century sampler.
Correspondence, chronological files, subject files, photographs, realia and one scrapbook.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Listening copies of audio and videotapes need to be made prior to use.
Acquisitions Information
Donation by Douglas J. Bennet, 2007.
Biographical Note
Douglas Joseph Bennet Jr. was born in Orange, New Jersey, on June 23, 1938, to Douglas Joseph Bennet Sr. and Phoebe Benedict Bennet. The family settled in Lyme, Connecticut. Bennet Sr. (Wesleyan class of 1933) was a businessman, and he also engaged in civic service. He was active in the Connecticut Democratic party and worked as executive secretary for Chester Bowles, then-governor of Connecticut, from 1949 to 1951. Phoebe Bennet was a graduate of Mt. Holyoke College and the New York School of Social Work. She was on the board of trustees for the Mansfield Training School and helped to establish the Office of Mental Retardation in the Connecticut State Department of Health. She was also on the board of the League of Women Voters in Lyme and the Lyme Board of Education. Bennet, Jr. was the oldest of five children. He graduated from Lyme High School in June 1955.
In the fall of 1955, Douglas Bennet, Jr. entered Wesleyan University as a freshman, class of 1959. During his four undergraduate years he showed a developing interest in history, government and the Russian language. He was co-president of the fraternity Alpha Chi Rho and was active in the Wesleyan chapter's decision to withdraw from the national organization as a result of racial and religious intolerance on the part of the parent organization. Although he would later self-deprecatingly describe this exercise by saying, "This operation involved a great deal of organizing and correspondence, and was one of the most inconsequential exercises imaginable," it was emblematic of his strongly developed social conscience. Bennet went on to receive his M.A. in history from the University of California, Berkeley in 1960 and then moved to Cambridge, MA, to begin work on his Ph.D. at Harvard.
Bennet's dissertation, The Idea of Kingship in 17th Century Russia, was competed in 1967. In the intervening years he had his first taste of international government work. Family friend and mentor Chester Bowles, who was then Ambassador to India, offered Bennet a position as his administrative assistant in New Delhi, India, in 1963. Bowles had been a member of the U.S. House of Representatives from Connecticut's second district from 1959 to 1961 and his vision and civic engagement were models for Bennet. Although Bennet had been thinking of going to Russia, he went instead to India, and spent two and a half years there. During that time he traveled extensively and wrote many speeches for Bowles and other administrators. He returned to Cambridge in January 1966 and finished his dissertation the following year.
With his experience as a speech writer, Bennet was able to land a job in Washington as speech writer for Vice President Hubert Humphrey. This was the beginning of almost 30 years in Washington, although his occupation was to change many times. Being a speech writer for Humphrey quickly swept Bennet into the heady and intense world of politics, especially when Humphrey ran for president in 1968. When Humphrey lost the election to Nixon, Bennet joined the staff of Thomas F. Eagleton, a senator from Missouri, in January 1969.
He worked for Eagleton as administrative assistant for the next four years. Bennet was active in the 1972 presidential election, in which Eagleton was a candidate for vice president, and helped to craft the Democratic platform that year. The controversy that broke in July regarding Eagleton's mental health gave Bennet on-the-ground training in crisis management. In April 1973, Bennet joined the staff of Abraham Ribicoff, the senator from his home state of Connecticut, again as administrative assistant. This was a short lived assignment as Bennet decided to make a run for the House of Representatives in 1974. His father, Bennet, Sr. ran for the same position in 1956. Bennet, Jr. did not win the primary and ceded the Democratic House nomination to Christopher Dodd.
In September 1974 Senator Edmund Muskie tapped him to be the first staff director of the newly formed Senate Budget Committee. Bennet held this post for the next two and a half years and it was his last in the legislative branch of government.
In 1977 Bennet reconnected with his 1960s roots in the State Department by becoming the Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional Relations. His two and a half years in this position gave him exposure to current foreign policy thinking. He traveled to Africa and China and was credited by President Carter for being instrumental in the signing of the Panama Canal Treaties in 1977. In July 1979 Carter nominated him to be administrator for the Agency for International Development (AID). Bennet held this post for the next year and a half until the 1980 election and the change of administration in January 1981. During his tenure at AID he traveled intensively, both nationally and internationally.
In January 1981 Bennet decided to spend much of that year at a slower pace, exploring his options and reconsidering his involvement with government. In December 1981 he accepted an offer by Chicago businessman, Richard J. Dennis, to be president of the Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies, a think tank started and bankrolled by Dennis. The mission of this organization was to act as a "bridge between the public and policymakers. By increasing the public's store of unbiased information, by opening up our national debate to fresh thinking about long-term solutions, and by working directly with policy-makers, the Center aims to help Americans and their leaders make constructive and farsighted policy choices." As president, Bennet was well positioned to make the best use of his extensive administrative and foreign policy experience. He worked hard for the next year and a half to further the Center's mission and was blindsided by Dennis's decision in June of 1983 to remove him as president. Bennet resigned at the end of June and spent the summer investigating the possibility of creating his own think tank, but lack of funding prevented it. In December 1983 it was announced that he would be the next president of National Public Radio.
National Public Radio was having its own problems in the early 1980s, having nearly declared bankruptcy just before Bennet became president. Fresh from his disappointment at the Roosevelt Center and bringing his impressive administrative skills to bear, he quickly turned NPR around, injecting solvency and a new sense of energy. Bennet took up the banner of freedom of speech and the first amendment as enthusiastically as he had foreign policy.
The pull of the State Department was still strong, however. After a break with government and 10 successful years at NPR, Bennet was ready to re-engage with global issues as Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs in 1993. For the next two years he worked closely with the United Nations working to improve the standard of living worldwide as he had, off and on, for thirty years.
Bennet had always retained a strong affection for Wesleyan University, his alma mater. He had been on its board of trustees for three years, from 1972 to 1975. His father was an alumnus and two of his children were alumni. So, in 1995 when he was asked to serve as Wesleyan's president, he accepted. He was president for 12 years, from 1995 to 2007, at which time he retired from public service.
Chronology List
1938 June 23 Born in Orange, NJ. Parents: Douglas Joseph Bennet and Phoebe Benedict Bennet
1959 June BA, Wesleyan University. Dutcher Prize in History.
1960 MA, History. University of California, Berkeley.
1963-1964 Assistant to the Economic Advisor, AID, New Delhi
1964-1966 Special assistant to Ambassador Chester Bowles, New Delhi
1967 PhD, Russian, medieval history, Harvard University
1967-1968 Assistant to Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey
1969-1973 Administrative assistant to Senator Thomas F. Eagleton
1972-1975 Member of Wesleyan University Board of Trustees
1973-1974 Administrative assistant to Senator Abraham Ribicoff
1974 Ran for House of Representatives, CT 2nd district
1974-1977 Staff director of Senate Budget Committee
1977 March - 1979 August Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional Relations
1979 August - 1981 January Administratior of the Agency for International Development (AID)
1981 December - 1983 June President of Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies
1983 December - 1993 May President of National Public Radio
1993 May - 1995 May Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs
1994 Honorary Doctor of Laws, Wesleyan University
1995-2007 15th President of Wesleyan University
1997 Honorary Doctor of Laws, Lawrence University
1999 Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters, Amherst College
2007 Honorary Doctor of Laws, Williams College
2008 Honorary Doctor of Laws, Trinity College
2008 Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters, University of Hartford
Collection Overview
Collection Arrangement
Series I: Executive service
Series II: Legislative service
Series III: Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies
Series IV: National Public Radio
Series V: Personal
Series VI: News Clips
As much as possible, the original folder titles have been maintained. In the container list below, these titles have been transcribed as accurately as possible. There is not a distinction made between the original folder titles and those provided by the processor.
Bennet's papers are filed in reverse date order, with the most recent in front. This arrangement has been maintained where found within a folder. The folders themselves are arranged in progressive date order. Thus, folders will be filed January to December, but within the January folder the first page would be January 31.
Series I: Executive service
Bennet worked for the State Department for much of his professional career. His first professional assignment, from 1963 to 1966, was in India as assistant to the economic advisor for the Agency for International Development, and then as special assistant to Ambassador Chester Bowles. Bennet was Assistant Secretary of State in two capacities: for Congressional Relations from 1977 to 1979, and for International Organization Affairs from 1993 to 1995. He also served as administrator for the Agency for International Development (AID) from 1979 to 1981. Bennet's executive service also included employment as a speech writer for Vice President Hubert Humphrey from 1967 to 1968. The collection contains realia from the 1968 Humphrey/Muskie presidential campaign.
This series contains "chron files," which are chronological correspondence. Files labeled "personal correspondence" are formal letters which relate to professional issues. The series also contains many speeches written by Bennet during his India days, as well as speeches written for Vice President Humphrey during his 1968 bid for the presidency. Bennet traveled extensively as administrator for AID and this sub-series contains many photographs.
Series II: Legislative service
Bennet was administrative assistant to two senators, Thomas F. Eagleton of Missouri from 1969 to 1973, and Abraham A. Ribicoff of Connecticut from 1973 to 1974. Bennet made an unsuccessful run for the House of Representatives in 1974, and went on to be staff director of the newly formed Senate Budget Committee from 1974 to 1977.
The Eagleton sub-series documents the fraught 1972 campaign with Eagleton as the running mate of George McGovern. The series documents Bennet's active role in framing the 1972 Democratic platform. There are also extensive newspaper clippings as well as files on the pivotal 18 days in July of 1972 when Eagleton was under siege and eventually withdrew. A PDF containing a list of magazines with coverage of this event which were removed from this part of the collection is available at: Magazines Removed (http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/MagazinesRemoved.pdf).
The documentation of Bennet's brief tenure as administrative assistant to Senator Ribicoff is minimal. It is represented only by "memos," which are the equivalent of "chron files." His departure was voluntary, driven by his decision to run for the House of Representatives in the 1974 election. This section of the collection is interesting for the insider's guide it provides to mounting a national campaign. This sub-series consists entirely of correspondence and subject files.
The Senate Budget Committee (SBC) sub-series contains chron files and subject files, including some speeches. The bulk of the series, however, is composed of the history of the SBC during its first two years. A PDF containing a list of government documents removed from this part of the collection is available at: Gov Docs Removed (http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/GovDocsRemoved.pdf).
Series III: Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies
The Roosevelt Center series documents Bennet's 18 months as president of a new public policy think tank. The papers document his active engagement in the creation of this organization. They also document his dismissal by the chairman of the board.
Because Bennet was between jobs from January to December of 1981 and from June to December of 1983, this series contains materials that precede and extend beyond his actual tenure at the Center.
Series IV: National Public Radio (NPR)
The bulk of Bennet's papers from his ten years as president of NPR are held at the National Public Broadcasting Archives, [http://www.lib.umd.edu/NPBA/].
The papers contained in this series give evidence of Bennet's success in bringing that organization from a tenuous financial position to one with a bright future. Much of the series is composed of speeches and articles from that period. There are also files on speech topics of particular interest to public radio. The subject files span the ten years, from early objectives to his eventual departure. A PDF containing a list of books removed from this part of the collection is available at: Books Removed (http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/BooksRemoved.pdf).
Subjects such as "AID correspondence" fall under this series due to their date range and original location within the papers, even though they are not directly related to NPR.
Series V: Personal
The personal series has three sub-series: correspondence, education, and subject files. Since these are primarily professional papers, personal correspondence is not well represented, although there is a collection of family Christmas cards sent by Bennet's parents throughout his childhood. There are also letters from his time in India from 1963 to 1965.
The education sub-series contains class notebooks, papers, and bibliographies from Bennet's years at Wesleyan, UC Berkeley, and Harvard. Of particular note is the file: "EQV: a history" [EQV stands for Esse Quam Videre]. This file documents Wesleyan's break with the fraternity Alpha Chi Rho on the grounds of intolerance, an event in which Bennet played a significant role.
Noteworthy in the subject files is a family scrapbook. The items in this scrapbook were not pasted in and are now housed in an acid free folder. Included are handwritten notes, presumably from Bennet's mother, explaining some of the documents. The scrapbook also contains an embroidered 19th century sampler.
Series VI: News Clips
News Clips are compilations of clippings prepared by the State Department's Office of Press Relations in the Bureau of Public Affairs. They were published daily. This series is a substantially complete run from 1993 March to 1995 May, during Bennet's time as Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Bennet, Douglas Joseph.; Eagleton, Thomas F., 1929-2007.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1998.; National Public Radio (U.S.); Roosevelt Center for American Policy Studies.; United States. Agency for International Development.; United States. Dept. of State.; Alpha Chi Rho.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.); Political campaigns.; Democratic Party (U.S.)--Platforms.; Scrapbooks.; Samplers (embroidery); Photographs.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Executive service, 1962-1995
  - State Department
    - India, 1963-1965
      - Correspondence
        - Proposal for India, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence, bulk 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - Leaving India, 1965 December-1966 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Chron files
        - 1963 August-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - 1964 January-March (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - 1964 April-August (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - 1964 September-October (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - 1964 November-1965 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - 1965 February-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - 1965 July (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - 1965 August-October (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - 1965 November-1966 January (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Subject files
        - Reference materials (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
      - Speeches and articles
        - Titles and topics, 1958-65 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Bowles: The Makings of a Just Society, 1963 December (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Education: Cornerstone of a Just Society, 1964 February 14 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - SID conference, Calcutta, 1964 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Two Stages of Indian Agricultural Development, 1964 February 16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - New York Times article - draft, 1964 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - Relations of American Populist New Deal Traditions to Overseas Development - draft, 1964 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - Agenda for India, 1964 March-June (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - U.N. Report on Planning of Economic Development in the U.S., 1964 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - Partners for growth and social justice, Calcutta, 1964 September 3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - American Foreign Policy after the Cold War, 1964 October 14 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        - U.S. Policy Toward India, Sagar University, 1964 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - For J.P. Lewis, Bombay - draft, 1964 November 18 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - Inaugural - draft, 1964 December 16 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - State of the union address - drafts, 1964 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - Johnson AID speech - draft, 1965 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - Inauguration, Sharavathy hydroelectric dam, 1965 January 24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - Critical Roadblocks to a More Prosperous and Dynamic India - draft, 1965 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 18)
        - Roundtable conference, New Delhi, 1965 February 24 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Struggle for Economic Democracy in India, Gauhati University, 1965 March 2 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Need for a More People-oriented Approach to Development - draft, 1965 April 7 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Ghandi as I Understood Him, New Delhi, 1965 May 5 (Box 2, Folder 22)
        - Impact of Modern Technology on the American Government, 1965 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 23)
        - Indian Achievements and Problems, 1965 July 2 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - The Second American Revolution, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Speech outline on PL 480 - draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Bowles: India - 1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional Relations, 1977 January-1979 July
      - Correspondence
        - Personal, spring, 1977 January-April (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
        - Personal, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
        - Personal, 1978 January-1979 July (Box 3, Folder 1-12)
      - Chron files
        - 1977 January-June (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
        - 1977 July-1978 May (Box 5, Folder 1-12)
        - 1978 June-1979 January (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
        - 1979 February-May (Box 7, Folder 1-15)
        - 1979 May-July (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
      - Subject files
        - Africa trip, 1978 November 27-30 (Box 8, Folder 6)
        - Audiotape: Douglas J. Bennet Jr., 1978 January 19 (Box 92 [oversize])
        - Certificate of appreciation, 1978 June 16-17 (Box 93 [oversize], Folder 3)
        - Chicago Council on Foreign Relations, 1977 October (Box 8, Folder 7)
        - China trip, 1978 January 2-17 (Box 8, Folder 8-13)
        - Crisis consultation, 1977 February-1978 January (Box 8, Folder 14)
        - Congressional access to information: Brubeck paper, 1977 February-November (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
        - Foreign policy articles, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
        - Funny stuff, 1975 June-1977 November (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
        - Legislative constraints, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
        - Memoranda of conversations, 1977 December-1979 June (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
        - Photographs, 1977 March-1979 July (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Photograph: signing of the Panama Canal treaties, 1977 September 7 (Box 93 [oversize], Folder 2)
        - Press, personal, 1974-1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - Press, 1977-1980 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Swearing-in, 1977 March 18 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Speeches
        - Speeches and appointments, 1977 June-1978 September (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Congressional relations policy, 1978 March 28 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - Speeches, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Administrator for the Agency for International Development (AID), 1979 July-1981 January
      - Correspondence
        - Personal, 1979 August-1981 January (Box 11, Folder 1-9)
        - Holiday cards, 1980 December (Box 11, Folder 10)
        - Congratulatory letters and responses, 1979 June-September (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
      - Chron files